Guide to the Thomas Hood Collection
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Thomas Hood collection
1827-1869
GEN MSS 53
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
0.2
(1 box)
The collection consists of correspondence from members of the Hood family: Jane Hood, Thomas Hood and Tom Hood; manuscripts by Thomas Hood, including some of the pieces published in "Odes and addresses to great people," an illustrated children's story, "Sir Amydor, A Romance," and other pieces; also includes a sketch of the grounds of Tom Hood's house at Wanstead, a photograph of Tom Hood, and a printed biographical notice of Thomas Hood.
Hood, Thomas, 1799-1845
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Ongoing collection of documents acquired by gift and purchase from various sources as indicated on individual folders, including a bequest from Ray Livingston Murphy, Yale class of 1951. For further information, consult the appropriate curator.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Scope and Contents
This finding aid encompasses accessions of single manuscripts and small groups of manuscripts and other papers, by or pertaining to the English poet and humorist, Thomas Hood (1799-1845), which the library has acquired from various sources, including a bequest from the collector Ray Livingston Murphy, Yale class of 1951. A few papers of Hood's son, Tom Hood (1835-1874), and his wife Jane Reynolds Hood (1792-1846) are also included. Material has been organized into 3 series: Correspondence, Writings, and Personal Papers.
Authors, English -- 19th century; Hood, Jane; Hood, Thomas, 1799-1845; Hood, Tom, 1835-1874
- CORRESPONDENCE, 1827-1869; Series I; 0.04; 12 folders
  Scope and Contents
  Series I, Correspondence, is organized into three subseries: Jane Reynolds Hood, Thomas Hood, and Tom Hood. Each subseries is arranged alphabetically by correspondent.
  - HOOD, JANE (REYNOLDS)
    - ALS to William Bernard Cooke, London, 1829 Nov 16 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - HOOD, THOMAS
    - ALS to Robert Balmanno, London, 1828 Mar 24 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - ALS to William Bradbury, London, [1829] (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - ALS to William Bernard Cooke, [1827] (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - ALS to May Elliot, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 5)
      Accompanied by Sir Amydor, A Romance: autograph manuscript story by Hood, with a notebook of pencil drawings illustrating the story; the name Jean Elliot appears on the inside cover of the notebook
    - 7 ALS to Dr. or Mrs. William Elliot, 1840-45 (Box 1, Folder 6)
      Printed in part in Memorials of Thomas Hood, 1860; the letter of 1840 Mar 4 also contains a letter from Jane Hood to Dr. Elliot
    - ALS to G.B., London., [1829] (Box 1, Folder 7)
      On the verso is the reply from the recipient to Thomas Hood, signed "G.B."
    - ALS to unidentified recipient. London., [1844?] (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - HOOD, TOM
    - ALS to Mr. Bryant, London, [1865?] (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - ALS to Samuel Carter Hall, London, 1865 Apr 21 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - ALS to George Wightwick, London, 1869 Sep 23 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - 7 ALS to unidentified recipients, London, 1865 (Box 1, Folder 12)
      Accompanied by an obituary notice and a photograph of Thomas Hood the younger and a biographical article on Thomas Hood the elder
- WRITINGS, n.d.; Series II; 16
  Series II, Writings, is arranged alphabetically by title.
  - "An Ancient Concert," autograph manuscript, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 13)
    On the same pages with "Pressure from Without" and "Preface" [to a ninth issue or edition]
  - "Bachelor's Dream," autograph manuscript, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - "The Character," autograph manuscript, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - "Drinking Song by a Member of a Temperance Society," autograph manuscript, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - "The Elland Meeting," autograph manuscript (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - "The Green Man," autograph manuscript, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - "Hints to the Horticultural," autograph manuscript, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 19)
    On the same pages with "Stanzas in a Shower Bath" and "Song from the Polish"
  - [Life of Edmund Waller], autograph manuscript (Box 1, Folder 20)
    Four non-consecutive pages concerning the life of Waller, with Hood's signature at the top above the heading "I: vol 1 - 84"
  - "Literary Reminiscences, No. 1," autograph manuscript, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 21)
    Fragment
  - "My Apology," autograph manuscript, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - "Murphy," autograph manuscript, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - "The New Lodger," autograph manuscript, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 24)
    On the same pages with "The Vision"
  - "Ode to Doctor Hahnemann," autograph manuscript, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 25)
    On the same pages with "Hitchen Hall" and "Sketches on the Road: The Wonderful Dog"
  - "Ode to Misses Green, Holland, and Monck Mason [?] on their late Balloon Expedition," autograph manuscript (Box 1, Folder 26)
    On the same pages with "Preface" [to an eighth issue or edition]
  - "Ode to Perry," autograph manuscript, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 27)
    With fragments of two other unidentified pieces
  - "The Portrait, Being an Apology for not making an Attempt on my own Life," autograph manuscript, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Sir Amydor: A Romance
    Related Archival Materials note
    See: box 1, folder 5
- PERSONAL PAPERS, n.d.; Series III
  - Hood, Tom. "Plan of his house and grounds at Wanstead," pen and ink sketch (Box 1, Folder 29)
    Endorsed in an unidentified hand: "Sketch of Hood's House by himself"